So starting...
okay, it says we're live. Okay, good morning. My name is Dan
Margulies, I am filling in for Rabbi Linzer while he's still in
Israel. Today is November 8th, it's the 19th of מרחשון, Marcheshvan, and
we have just started מסכת מכות Masechet Makkot yesterday. Thank you, big
thank you to Michal. I heard she did a wonderful job with
introduction, introducing all the themes and ideas of the מסכת, Masechet, which
means I don't have to explain anything. And we're going to pick
up around seven lines down in the wide lines on ב עמוד
ב bet amud bet where it says אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rav
Chisda. So this, we're in the middle of a discussion which is
why, why
do עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, why are they off the hook for
paying כופר? kofer? That is if עדים זוממים edim zomemim would come
to testify
to—I find that humorous, high school kids highlighting everything—so if עדים זוממים
edim zomemim would be coming to force someone to pay כופר, kofer,
this is a certain kind, certain kinds of payments that come about
either in a case where because of physical assault a man causes
a woman to have a miscarriage in some way, or in certain
kinds of cases of oxen we remember back from בבא קמא Bava
Kamma we have כופר kofer that gets paid by שור תם. shor
tam. So there are other kinds of cases where you would have
a כופר. kofer. So if the witnesses come to testify about someone
that they would be forced to pay כופר kofer and then the
witnesses are proved to be זוממים, zomemim, so we actually don't make
them pay the כופר kofer in reciprocity, it's an exception to the
general rule of reciprocal punishment. So we were saying where does that
from? And we said, oh, כופרא כפרה. kufra kapara. So it's based
on the principle that כופר, kofer, the כופר kofer payment is a
כפרה, kapara, is an atonement
for the crime, it's not actually...
restitutive... I'm not sure if that's a word... it is now... restorative,
restitution type of payment but it's a payment that by giving that
money you effect the כפרה kapara for the sin of the crime.
So if that's the case, so הני לאו בני כפרה נינהו. ha
hanei lav bar kapara ninhu. So for the עדים זוממים edim zomemim
they didn't actually do the crime that the כופר kofer comes to
bring כפרה kapara for, so there would be no need for them
to pay the כופר. kofer. So it's an interesting exception to the
rule.
But now our גמרא Gemara brings in the opinion of רב חסדא
Rav Chisda by asking מאן תנא כופרא כפרה? Man tanna kufra kapara?
So who is the one who says that כופר kofer is a
כפרה, kapara, is an atonement type of payment? So אמר רב חסדא,
Amar Rav Chisda, רב חסדא Rav Chisda says רבי ישמעאל בנו של
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה היא. Rabbi Yishmael bno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka hi. So he says it's the opinion of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Yishmael, the son of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה. Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka.
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka himself an interesting תנא,
Tanna, and this רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael his son. So it says
דתניא De-tanya we have two different opinions in a ברייתא Baraita ונתן
פדיון נפשו. Ve-natan pidyon nafsho. This is in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma,
and it says he has to pay פדיון נפשו pidyon nafsho a
redemption for his life. דמי ניזק. Demei nizak. So the תנא קמא's
Tanna Kamma position is that you pay according to the value of
the one who was injured. That is the כופר kofer payment goes
according to the person who was injured. רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר דמי מזיק. Rabbi Yishmael bno shel Rabbi Yochanan
ben Beroka omer demei mazik.
And
he says that actually no, the payment goes according to the value—and
again these value assessments are דמים—it's damim an assessment of how much
this person would be able to be sold for as a slave
on the slave market, things like that. Okay. So this מחלוקת machloket
whether you pay דמי ניזק demei nizak or דמי מזיק demei mazik
sounds like, at least in part, that it could be because רבי
ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה Rabbi Yishmael bno shel Rabbi
Yochanan ben Beroka his opinion is that the כופר kofer is about
a כפרה kapara for myself. If I did this crime and now
my value is being assessed to pay
afterward, oh, it's because I have to pay the value of my
own life as a כפרה kapara for myself. But if it's דמי
ניזק demei nizak you're paying for the person who was injured, then
it makes sense that you would say it's not about כפרה, kapara,
it's about some sort of restoration, some sort of something to do
with the person you injured. Okay. So מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? mai
lav behai kamiflegi? No, it could be an alternative
interpretation—isn't it obvious
that this is what I just said, that also מאי לאו בהא
קמיפלגי דמר סבר כופרא ממונא? mai lav behai kamiflegi demar savar kufra
mamona? One says that כופרא, kufra, the כופר kofer payment is ממונא,
mamona, it's a monetary payment, that's why you would pay דמי ניזק
demei nizak the one according to the damage. ומר סבר כופרא כפרה.
Umarsavar kufra kapara. And רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says that it goes
according to that it's כפרה, kapara, so it goes like דמי מזיק
demei mazik the person who caused the damage. אמר רבא, Amar Rappa,
רבא Rappa disagrees with רב חסדא Rav Chisda and says לא דכולי
עלמא כופרא כפרה. lo dekuli alma kufra kapara. Everyone agrees that כופרא
kufra is actually is a כפרה kapara payment. So in fact we
don't need to say oh, מאן תנא, man tanna, it's actually every
תנא Tanna holds that כופרא כפרה. kufra kapara. והכא בהא קמיפלגי. ve-hacha
behai kamiflegi. So this is actually what their debate is about, that
is between תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. מר
סבר בדמי ניזק שמינן. Mar savar bedemei nizak shaminan. One says, that
is the first opinion תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says, we assess according
to the value of the ניזק, nizak, the one who was injured.
ומר סבר בדמי מזיק שמינן. Umarsavar bedemei mazik shaminan. And the רבי
ישמעאל's Rabbi Yishmael position is that we just assess... according to the
value of the person who caused the damage. Now, that's a sort
of non-answer. Oh, why would we do that? So in at least
in part, it's going to be based on the analogous case or
based on the juxtaposition of the case. So מאי טעמא דדרבנן? mai
ta'ama d'rabbanan? Why do the תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma's position, the רבנן's
rabbanan's position, why would we say דמי ניזק? d'mei nizak? So נאמר
השתא למטה ונאמר השתא למעלה. ne'emar hashta l'mata v'ne'emar hashta l'mala. So
each of them is mentioned, the דמי ניזק,
d'mei nizak, the two juxtaposed cases, the case of the כופר kofer
and the case in the case, so if you look in רש״י,
Rashi, it's like in the third line in
רש״י Rashi of the wide lines, sorry, second wide
line,
sorry, so it's like the fourth line, נאמר השתא למעלה בנוגף אשה
הרה. ne'emar hashta l'mala b'nogef isha hara. So in a case where
someone, like I said, assaults a pregnant woman, כאשר ישית עליו בעל
האשה. ka'asher yashit alav ba'al ha'isha. So in that in that case
it's explicit that the כופר kofer payment goes according to the one
the person who was injured. The assessment of the of the value,
and therefore
רבנן rabbanan learn it as an analogous case, and they they say
so in both of them we would say that you should go
by דמי ניזק. d'mei nizak. Okay, ונאמר השתא למעלה. v'ne'emar hashta l'mala.
So מה להלן בניזק אף כאן בניזק. ma lehalan b'nizak af kan
b'nizak. We both of them we go by the one who was
injured. For רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, ונתן פדיון נפשו כתיב, u'natan pidyon
nafsho ketiv, it says ונתן פדיון נפשו. u'natan pidyon nafsho. You have
to pay back the value of נפשו, nafsho, of his life. ורבנן,
v'rabbanan,
so
okay, אין, in,
so ורבנן v'rabbanan they say, so פדיון נפשו כתיב. pidyon nafsho ketiv.
So what do they do with the fact that it says פדיון
נפשו, pidyon nafsho, which is a proof for רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Ishmael?
So they say נפשו כתיב. nafsho ketiv. It says
'his life'. מיהו כדשיימינן בניזק שיימינן. mihu k'deshayminan b'nizak shayminan. So that
no, it's sort of still remains ambiguous and we can interpret it
to mean that you should assess based on the value of the
ניזק nizak and not the value of the מזיק. mazik. Okay. Okay,
next. If
it's a payment for yourself, but in terms of,
right, but the
value,
right, the amount, exactly. So that's the point that in רב פפא's
Rav Pappa's interpretation, everyone agrees כופרא כפרה, kufra kapara, the question is
what value or whose whose price, whose דמים damim should you assess
to use for that כפרה. kapara. So it still would get you
to the point of saying, oh, we can still use the value
of the ניזק, nizak, but the מזיק mazik is the one who's
paying and it's still כפרה kapara for his his life. Okay. The
next exception to to the laws in עדים זוממים edim zomemim we
learn אין נמכרים בעבד עברי. ein nimkarim b'eved ivri.
So now again, witnesses come and testify a person stole something and
he doesn't have the money to pay for it, so he should
be sold as an עבד עברי. eved ivri. So and now they're
proved to be עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, so should we say, oh,
so they should be sold as עבד עברי eved ivri instead, or
not? That's the question. Alternatively, עדים זוממים edim zomemim come and testify
this person stole something and he can just pay back the money,
and then instead they're shown to be עדים זוממים edim zomemim but
they don't actually have any money, so maybe we should sell them
as עבד עברי eved ivri to pay for the value that they
tried to force someone else to pay? That's the question. How far
do we extend, how much do we see עבד עברי eved ivri
as a distinct institution from just the paying back the value of
what was stolen or not? Is it just a mechanism to pay
or is it actually a punishment or or an institution in its
own right? Okay, so that's the question.
If it was just a punishment then you wouldn't be able to
get out of it if you had enough money to pay. So
it's only, so to me it seems it's only really a mechanism,
which means what they wanted to do, they didn't want to make
him an עבד עברי, eved ivri, they wanted to to have him
on the hook for the value of whatever it is he stole,
regardless of how we got it back. If we got it back
by being an עבד עברי eved ivri or if we got
it, in which case
then the logical inference to that is, regardless of what they wanted
to do for him and regardless of how much money they have,
regardless of how much money he has, so it makes no difference
if he has money or no money or they have money or
no money, they should always,
עבד עברי eved ivri is just a mechanism to pay the value.
So let's see how the גמרא Gemara flushes it out. אין נמכרים
בעבד עברי, ein nimkarim b'eved ivri, סבר רב המנונא למימר הני מילי
היכא דאית ליה לדידיה. savar Rav Hamnuna l'meimar hani mili heicha d'is
lei l'didei. So רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna said it makes sense to
understand that this is in a case where he has the money,
that is the the the defendant in the case. דאילו דאיהו לא
מזדבן אינהו נמי לא מזדבני. d'ilu d'ihu lo mizdaban inhu nami lo
mizdabni. So
and from the fact that he would not have been sold, that
is the defendant, then the witnesses also should not be sold as
slaves because the defendant was never going to be sold as a
slave himself. אבל היכא דלית ליה לדידיה, aval heicha d'leis lei l'didei,
but if the defendant doesn't have any money, אף על גב דאית
להו לדידהו מזדבני. af al gav d'is lehu l'didhu mizdabni.
So then even if the witnesses do have the money to pay
the value that they could have would have needed to pay to
get to pay what he was on the hook for, nonetheless they
should be sold as slaves because sort of as if they knew
when they were testifying against him and they were conspiring against him
that he didn't have the money to pay for this alleged theft,
therefore they knew what they were trying to get him to be
had done to him was to have him sold as עבד עברי,
Eved Ivri, therefore the punishment they should get is to be sold
as עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. That's רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna according to
the פנים יפות. Panim Yafot. Okay. Okay, so Michael's point is saying,
oh, but if the whole point of עבד עברי Eved Ivri is
just to pay back the money, then well they have the money,
they should just be able to pay cash.
And they can, right?
Even if they're sold as an עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, that's like
two seconds later, right,
so they could pay cash. Right, but the point is, is it
an option for them, or is it like, like is that only
if they choose to do so, or is it automatic, or what?
So that's רב המנונא'ס Rav Hamnuna's argument at least. Okay, okay, ו-
ve-
so really it shouldn't say, it should say הכי איתמר. hachi itmar.
So הכי איתמר hachi itmar ולימרו ליה velimru leh אי אנת הוה
לך i ant hava lach מי הוה מזדבן. mi hava mizdaban. So
because you could say back, so אי אנת הוה לך, i ant
hava lach, if I had had the money, so מי הוה מזדבן,
mi hava mizdaban, would I have been sold? So אנן, anan, so
אנן נמי לא מזדבנינן. anan nami lo mizdabninan. So we also shouldn't
be sold. That is, since he, that is since the עדים זוממים
edim zomemim can respond, since he, that is since you the defendant
would not have been sold as a slave because you, so they're
saying in response, that is right. Okay. So then, what does it
say?
Oh wait, sorry.
So אבל היכא דלית ליה לא לדידיה ולא לדידהו aval heicha delait
leh lo ledideh velo ledidhu okay. So הכי איתמר. hachi itmar. So
they can say back, so that's a response to רב המנונא, Rav
Hamnuna, ולימרו ליה velimru leh they could say to him, אי אנת
הוה לך i ant hava lach if you had had, מי הוה
מזדבן
mi hava mizdaban would
you have been sold as a slave? No. אנן נמי לא מזדבנינן
anan
nami
lo mizdabninan we also shouldn't be sold as slaves because we have
the money to be able to pay. That is it's only an
opportunity if that you have, you can pay back the money, it
doesn't matter. Okay. אלא, ela, סבר רב המנונא למימר. savar Rav Hamnuna
lemimar. So we have to amend or, or רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna
offers a second interpretation. Rather, למימר lemimar הני מילי היכא דאית ליה
או לדידיה או לדידהו. hani mili heicha deit leh o ledideh o
ledidhu. It's whether either of them has. אבל היכא דלית ליה לא
לדידיה ולא לדידהו aval heicha delait leh lo ledideh velo ledidhu but
if neither of them has the money, מזדבני. mizdabni. So then they
would be sold as slaves because then the defendant would have for
sure gone as a slave and they don't have the recourse to
be able to pay instead, so they also should go as slaves.
What? So אמר ליה רבא amar leh Rava since there was an
issue, he says עין תחת עין. ayin tachat ayin. Right, so then
the point is, so רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna says under normal circumstances
אין נמכרים בעבד עברי ein nimkarim beeved ivri but there's a specific
exception of a case where they don't have the money and he
doesn't have the money that actually they could go as slave. So
they say אמר ליה רבא. amar leh Rava. No, רבא Rava says
actually the whole point of the משנה mishna to teach you דווקא
davka that case, that is the case where you could have thought
that they would have been sold as slaves. Nonetheless, it says ונמכר
בגנבתו. venimkar bignivato. He should be sold to pay back for his
theft. אמרה רחמנא amra rachmana בגנבתו ולא בזממו. bignivato velo bizmamo. You're
only sold for having stolen and not for conspiracy. That is the
whole issue of the reciprocal punishment
does not extend to the, to עבד
עברי. eved ivri. It's a special exception. Okay. משום רבי עקיבא אמרו.
mishum Rabbi Akiva amru.
So what does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say in our משנה? mishna?
Sorry, page got stuck.
So רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's position in the משנה, mishna, wait. Oh
sorry, yeah.
Not in the משנה.
mishna. He's not in the משנה. mishna. He's in the ברייתא, braita,
right.
Yeah, there's a תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan two lines down or so.
Yeah, yeah, sorry. Yeah, yeah. The five, the four things. So רבי
עקיבא אומר אף אינם משלמים על פי עצמן. Rabbi Akiva omer af
einam meshalmim al pi atzman. So they don't have to pay back
by their own testimony. So what's the point from רבי עקיבא? Rabbi
Akiva? מאי טעמא דרבי עקיבא? mai taama deRabbi Akiva? קסבר kasavar קנסא
הוא. kenasa hu. So the whole, he, רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's understanding
of this whole construct is that it's a קנס. kenas. וקנס אין
משלם על פי עצמו. vekenas ein meshalem al pi atzmo.
That is wait a second. When we say that you testify about
someone stole something and they have to pay back the money, that's
not a קנס. kenas. That's ממון, mamon, that's, that's the amount you
owe them money. But the punishment that gets imposed on עדים זוממים
edim zomemim for having accused someone of owing money would be a
קנס. kenas. That's according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. What's interesting about
that and perhaps exceptional among the examples of קנס kenas that we
have in הלכה, halacha, and that's why this becomes very interesting, is
that קנס kenas almost always is a fixed amount. It's precisely defined
in the תורה. Torah. But and and that's one of the defining
features, the difference between קנס kenas and ממון. mamon. קנס kenas is
a fixed quantity. So here רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says actually the
sliding scale variable punishment that goes for עדים זוממים edim zomemim is
itself a קנס. kenas. So it's actually interesting that it's a sliding
scale קנס. kenas. Okay. So מאי טעמא דרבי עקיבא קסבר קנסא הוא
וקנס אין משלם על פי עצמו mai taama deRabbi Akiva kasavar kenasa
hu vekenas ein meshalem al pi atzmo because we have the general
principle מודה בקנס פטור. modeh bekenas patur. If you admit your liability
in a case of קנס, kenas, you actually get yourself off the
hook because sort of the whole point of the קנס kenas is
to force you to confess or to force you to own up
to your crime rather than to actually get the money paid. So
it's actually an interesting exception. Okay. אמר רבא amar Rava תדע שהרי
לא עשו מעשה ונהרגים. teda sheharei lo asu maaseh veneheragim. So wait
a second. These are people תדע, Teda, תדע Teda is we're going
to make an inference from he's saying back to the proposed suggestion
of Rabbi Akiva, that is שלא עשו מעשה ונהרגים ומשלמים, shelo asu
ma'aseh venahargim umeshalmim, that is, so either so we should say no,
no, no, you can't just get yourself off the hook by being
מודה. modeh. That is, Rabbi Akiva's position was אמרו אף אין משלמים
על פי עצמן. amru af ein meshalmim al pi atzman. So אין
משלמים על פי עצמן ein meshalmim al pi atzman would mean oh
it's like a קנס. knas. But wait a second, מודה בקנס פטור.
modeh biknas patur.
So you could say wait, so the fact that we're going to
execute them is is קנס knas also? So then oh we're going
to execute you say oh I'm מודה, modeh, right? So at what
point does it become a bit absurd? So he says תדע שהרי
לא עשו מעשה ונהרגים. teda sheharei lo asu ma'aseh venahargim.
He thinks about the whole concept of עדים זוממים edim zomemim
as a קנס, knas, is that what you're trying to say? Right,
that's what Rabbi Akiva sounds like he's saying. And Rava is pushing
back and saying if you open up that possibility then now wait
a second you have people who didn't do anything, that is they
didn't do any capital crime but they were עדים זוממים edim zomemim
and we're going to kill them. So he says ונהרגים ומשלמים. venahargim
umeshalmim. We should just force, we impose this punishment on them no
matter what. So אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, תדע, Teda, שהרי
ממון ביד בעלים ומשלמים. sheharei mamon beyad be'alim umeshalmim. But this is
a special exception anyway because nobody stole anything and you're paying back
money anyway. So that is either right that we're we're going to
kill them and make them pay the money or we're going to
pay back the money even though nobody lost anything.
So he made Rav Nachman? He made Rava mean? Well so that's
the point, is this a special exception? This payment is different than
normal cases. Okay, so we're going to see. So מאי ניהו? mai
nihu? So מאי ניהו דלא עשו מעשה? mai nihu shelo asu ma'aseh?
What case are we talking about? So what is it that they
didn't do a מעשה, ma'aseh, they didn't do any action? We're on
the top of ג עמוד א. gimmel amud alef. היינו דרבא. hainu
deRava. That's what Rava was talking about. אימא וכן אמר רב נחמן
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. eima vechen amar Rav Nachman amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav. So what case are we talking about? עד זומם
משלם לפי חלקו. ed zomem meshalem lefi chelko. A single עד זומם
ed zomem pays the monetary restitution according to his percentage stake in
the in the conspiracy. So מאי משלם לפי חלקו? mai meshalem lefi
chelko? אילימא להאי משלם פלגא ולהאי משלם פלגא? eileima lehai meshalem palga
ulehai meshalem palga? Perhaps we should understand that of the two witnesses
each one should pay half. So תנינא, tanina, we learned in the
next coming up משנה mishnah later, משלמין בממון ואין משלמין במלקות. meshalmin
bemamon ve'ein meshalmin bemalkot. When we're we can subdivide the financial liabilities
in a case of עדים זוממים edim zomemim among the different witnesses
but not the punitive whether it's lashes or whether it's a capital
crime or something like that. The capital and corporal punishment doesn't get
subdivided. If you have if you're trying to force someone to get
forty lashes you don't say each each witness gets twenty. You say
each witness gets forty because the punishment is of forty lash, well
really thirty-nine and then how do you divide thirty-nine in half? But
okay. אלא כגון דהוזם חד מינייהו. ela kegon de'uhzam chad mineihu. No
maybe what happened was there was a group of witnesses and only
one of them was shown to have been עד זומם. ed zomem.
דמשלם פלגא דידיה. demeshalem palga dideih. Maybe he'll pay only his half.
ומי משלם? umi meshalem? So but wait a second does he would
he really have to pay in such a case? That is in
a case where only one of the conspiracy only one of the
witnesses was proven to have been עד זומם? ed zomem? והתניא, vehatanya,
אין עד זומם משלם ממון עד שיוזמו שניהם. ein ed zomem meshalem
mamon ad sheyuzmu sheneihem. For we have a ברייתא braita that says
that actually in order to make any of them pay you have
to prove that the entire group of witnesses were conspiratorial. That is
they have to achieve the status of becoming עד זומם. ed zomem.
Okay, so אמר רבא, Amar Rava, באומר עדות שקר העדתי. be'omer edut
sheker ha'edati.
When someone comes forward and says oh actually my testimony was false.
כל כמיניה? kol kaminieih? Is that really true? כיון שהגיד שוב אינו
חוזר ומגיד. keivan shehigid shuv eino chozer umagid. Who says that we
would allow him to disqualify his own testimony? Once you testify it's
on the docket you can't go back and change things. אלא באומר
העדנו והוזמנו בבית דין פלוני. ela be'omer ha'ednu vehuzmanu beveit din ploni.
So they show up and said we already testified in someone else's
court and we were shown to be עדים זוממים edim zomemim in
that same court over there and now so he's saying I want
to pay this money. So that's the point where we would say
that you're not allowed to משלם על פי עצמו. meshalem al pi
atzmo. You can't just show up and say oh I'm an עד
זומם ed zomem and I owe this person money. That's not not
allowed.
Wait wait what is going on here?
They're trying to say what is the case of
לא עשו מעשה? lo asu ma'aseh? The case where where how can
you say
that would be משלם על פי עצמו meshalem al pi atzmo and
the challenge to that was but they didn't do anything that is
the case wasn't resolved to that point or something like that. So
the point of oh what is it משלם על פי עצמו? meshalem
al pi atzmo? What kind of self-obligation are you putting yourself into
that would circumvent the question of מודה בקנס פטור? modeh biknas patur?
Because that was the whole issue we had with Rabbi Akiva. So
here he's saying oh you show up in בית דין beit din
and say oh I was shown to proven to be עד זומם
ed zomem in a different court and now I'm coming to come
forward to actually pay the debt. Okay, so כמאן דלא כרבי עקיבא.
keman de'lo kerabi akiva. That's actually... That actually doesn't accord with Rabbi
Akiva's position. דאי כרבי עקיבא *de-i k'Rabbi Akiva*, if it were like
Rabbi Akiva's position, הא אמר אף אינו משלם על פי עצמו *ha
amar af eino meshallem al pi atzmo*, because Rabbi Akiva says you
can't turn yourself in to pay for עדים זוממים Eidim Zomemim *edim
zomemim*. אלא באומר העדנו והוזמנו בבית דין של פלוני *ella be-omer he-adnu
ve-huzamnu be-veis din shel ploni*, rather it must be a case where
they show up and say we testified and were shown to be
עדים זוממים *edim zomemim* in another court, וחיובונו ממון *ve-hiyyevunu mamon*,
and they told us that we're obligated to pay this certain amount
of money. סלקא דעתך אמינא *salka da'atakh amina*, I might
have thought, כיון דלחבריה לא מצי מחייב *keivan de-le-havrei
lo matzi mechayev*, since he can't force his friend to pay, that
is, the two witnesses show up together and one of them says
I have to pay 100 dollars and the other one doesn't say
anything, you can't force, you can't say wait a second but you
were there with me the whole time, what about, but then it's
עד אחד בממון *ed echad be-mamon* is not enough to force him
to pay, איהו נמי לא מחייב *ihu nami lo mechayev*, so would
you say that he also can't force himself to pay? קא משמע
לן *ka mashma lan*. So that's what this whole piece comes to
teach, which is that there is a way that's not משלם על
פי עצמו *meshallem al pi atzmo* where the עד זומם *ed zomem*
can show up and volunteer to pay back the money that he
owes and that would be acceptable. Okay. And the next משנה mishnah
*mishna*, מעידים *me-idim*... Yeah? But when they're saying they're from a previous
court, that they were found to be זוממים *zomemim*, is it the
same case that was being brought from the previous court to this
court? It's not even a same, it's not a case anymore, right?
There was a case, they were shown to be עדים זוממים *edim
zomemim*, and then it was registered in the court docket, you know,
פלוני *Ploni* owes 200 dollars. And then you show up at a
different court and you say okay I want to pay, I want
to pay back the money. So that's not משלם על פי עצמו
*meshallem al pi atzmo* because that's not, now you're not being מודה
*modeh* to anything, now you're just showing up and actually paying back
something that you were.
So the only way that would happen then is before the court
has ruled?
Right. That would be משלם על פי עצמו *meshallem al pi atzmo*
because that, but that's the only problem of מודה בקנס פטור *modeh
biknas patur* also.
So then they go to another court?
Right, because otherwise it will just be within the same case, exactly.
Okay. So כמאן *k'man*? דלא כרבי עקיבא *d'lo k'Rabbi Akiva*. It actually
doesn't accord with Rabbi Akiva's position. דאי כרבי עקיבא *de-i k'Rabbi Akiva*,
if it were like Rabbi Akiva, הא אמר אף אינו משלם על
פי עצמו *ha amar af eino meshallem al pi atzmo*. אלא באומר
העדנו והוזמנו בבית דין פלוני וחיובונו ממון *ella be-omer he-adnu ve-huzamnu be-veis
din ploni ve-hiyyevunu mamon*. סלקא דעתך אמינא *salka da'atakh amina*, כיון דלחבריה
לא מצי מחייב *keivan de-le-havrei lo matzi mechayev*, since he can't force
his friend to pay, that is, the two witnesses show up together
and one of them says I have to pay 100 dollars and
another one doesn't say anything, you can't force, you can't say wait
a second but you were there with me the whole time, what
about, but then it's עד אחד בממון *ed echad be-mamon* is not
enough to force him to pay, איהו נמי לא מחייב *ihu nami
lo mechayev*, so would you say that he also can't force himself
to pay? קא משמע לן *ka mashma lan*. So that's what this
whole piece comes to teach, which is that there is a way
that's not משלם על פי עצמו *meshallem al pi atzmo* where the
עד זומם *ed zomem* can show up and volunteer to pay back
the money that he owes and that would be acceptable. Okay. And
the next משנה mishna, *mishna*, מעידים *me-idim*... Yeah? But when they're saying
they're from a previous court, that they were found to be זוממים
*zomemim*, is it the same case that was being brought from the
previous court to this court? It's not even a same, it's not
a case anymore, right? There was a case, they were shown to
be עדים זוממים *edim zomemim*, and then it was registered in the
court docket, you know, פלוני *Ploni* owes 200 dollars. And then you
show up at a different court and you say okay I want
to pay the money. Right, you're just showing up and actually paying
back something that you were. So the only way that would happen
then is before the court has ruled? Right. That would be משלם
על פי עצמו *meshallem al pi atzmo*. But that's the only problem
of מודה בקנס פטור *modeh biknas patur* also. So then they go
to another court? Right, because otherwise it will just be within the
same case, exactly. Okay. So let's say then, you know, you see
the ruling coming then you say I'm an עד זומם *ed zomem*.
Then would you still get off the hook or would or would
the court just finish it? I'm not sure. I think at that
point you're not really allowed to say much, so because אין חוזר
ומגיד *ein chozer u-maggid*, right? אין אדם חוזר ומגיד *ein adam chozer
u-maggid*, things like that. And then basically then you still end up
paying even by that same court even if you admit it? Right.
If you admitted it
at
a point where we're
not allowed to, where
we're not listening to you anymore, something like that, right.
So,
there by, right. So the מודה בקנס *modeh biknas* at some point
like,
right. It's like before the court is finally able to say you're
חייב *hayyav* to pay XYZ and then, like, after they say that
then if you admit to it then whatever, who cares? But before
that, so I don't know exactly about when it would matter, but
there is a narrow window.
So I guess it would be like, you know, you see these
other witnesses coming and you know that oh oh, I know those
guys. They're going to...
Something like that. Right, before the other guys testify, right,
that's it, I'm a זומם *zomem*.
I'm an עד זומם *ed zomem*. Right, something like that. You can't
do that, because, exactly. That's exactly this point here, which is that
כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד *keivan she-higgid, shuv eino chozer u-maggid*.
Once you've registered your testimony, you can't go back and amend your
testimony later. You can't add something in later or clarify something.
But also you can't testify against yourself, right?
At least in part. For sure testifying against yourself, but also, meaning,
a more general rule is you're not allowed to go back and
amend testimony. You gave your testimony, now you're done. You go sit
down. We don't need you anymore.
So what happens in, like, in our court system? Somebody admits that
they lied to a court, this wouldn't be admissible in what we're
discussing?
I have no idea about the American court system.
No, no, I'm saying... Oh, our system? Yes, is that would not
be admissible in what we're discussing here? Can you say afterwards that
you lied in your testimony?
Well, we would ignore you in הלכה halacha *halakha*, yeah.
But when? Any point? Once you said it, that's it?
Well, you go and you testify, it's registered in court as a
true testimony. You can't go back later and testify about it. There's
no such thing. But somebody else can come and say עמנו הייתם
emanu heyitem. *immanu hayyitem*, right? Right, not him. Not him. because he
lied is of the same class. It's עדות בהכחשה, they contradict each
other, but it doesn't... it weakens it, but it doesn't eliminate it.
The way to destroy testimony is הזמה. hazama. You have to say
there was no way for you to have been able to have
had this information. עמנו הייתם. Anyway, we have to keep going.
Yeah. Two conflicting testimonies don't they just cancel each other out?
They can cancel each other out in different ways. They can cancel
each other out but that's what I mean is that it is
because of an impasse. It doesn't eliminate... anyway, there's a lot, a
lot more about this.
Is this only capital punishment?
No, this could apply to any kind of a case. Okay. We
keep going. Yeah, Charles, sorry.
Oh yeah, in secular world there's a problem with witnesses who we
can't whether you believe or not as well. I mean I'm not
a lawyer but...
For sure. Okay, so the next משנה mishna says מעידים אנו את
איש פלוני שגירש את אשתו. me'idim anu et ish ploni shegeresh et
ishto. We testify about so-and-so that he divorced his wife ולא נתן
לה כתובתה velo natan lah ketubatah and he didn't pay the כתובה.
ketubah. והלא בין היום ובין למחר סופו ליתן לה כתובה. vehalo bein
hayom uvein lemachar sofo liten lah ketubah. But the point is, wait
a second, he already has divorced her. We're admitting like everybody agrees
that they got divorced. The question is whether he paid the כתובה
ketubah or not. So the difference will just be how long has
passed or how long the woman has the money of the כתובה
ketubah in her control. So עומדים כמה אדם רוצה ליתן בכתובה זו...
omdim kama adam rotze liten beketubah zu...
I'm sorry, no. Meaning no, that he didn't pay it? I mean
maybe he paid it already?
No, we don't know exactly. So the difference will be whether he's
going to pay today or whether he already paid. Right? But so
wait a second. So look, meaning סופו ליתן כתובה sofo liten ketubah
meaning...
sorry one second. מעידים אנו את איש פלוני שגירש את אשתו ולא
נתן לה כתובה. me'idim anu et ish ploni shegeresh et ishto velo
natan lah ketubah. Okay. והלא בין היום ובין למחר סופו ליתן לה
כתובתה. vehalo bein hayom uvein lemachar sofo liten lah ketubatah. The point
is no matter what he will have paid her the כתובה, ketubah,
so עומדים כמה אדם רוצה ליתן בכתובה של זו שאם נתאלמנה או
נתגרשה ואם מת יירשנה בעלה. omdim kama adam rotze liten beketubah shel
zu she'im nitalmena o nitgarsha ve'im met yirashena ba'alah. So we do
a risk assessment between the cost is if the wife predeceases
the husband then the wife's estate will have to pay the husband
then it'll belong to the husband. And then we do the benefit
analysis is but if the husband predeceases the wife or he divorces
her then pay the כתובה. ketubah. So we balance those against each
other and say, okay, so how much would this investment be worth
to someone? It carries a certain amount of risk, it carries a
certain amount of dividend and then the question will be so on
the investment market how much would such a כתובה ketubah be worth?
That is, the כתובה ketubah is assessed based on the liability of
the wife's estate and the benefits from the husband's כתובה. ketubah. So
the גמרא Gemara says כיצד שמין, keitzad shamin, how do we do
this assessment? אמר רב חסדא בבעל. amar Rav Chisda beva'al. We assess
it based on the husband. That is, according to this specific husband,
about how much his whether who how much money does he have
and all these things. We would go and ask around how much
whether he's going to die soon or not, do we think he'll
divorce her soon or not? Those kinds of questions. Okay. ורב נתן
בר אושעיא אומר באשה. veRav Natan bar Oshaya omer be'ishah. We take
the assessment based on the woman's perspective. That is, how much was
her estate and how many liabilities were there in her dowries and
things like that. דאמר רב פפא באשה ובכתובתה de'amar Rav Papa be'ishah
uveketubatah meaning
it's how much this is worth. I understand בעל ba'al versus אשה.
ishah.
Right,
but the point is because it's an assessment you have to bring
in all of the different bits of risk in order to... right.
So the question is how expansive of a definition of the different
liabilities and the different risks involved in this כתובה ketubah would we
use to actually assess the value of this כתובה. ketubah.
Is this to define how much the זוממין zomemim have to pay?
Tangentially, yes. But also just in general to find out... right right,
because the זוממין zomemim are going to have to pay not the
value of the כתובה, ketubah, but actually the difference in between the
value of the כתובה ketubah and the cost-benefit, right? So because this
כתובה ketubah even though right it says 200, but really maybe it's
actually worth less because it's a low... we don't know who'll die
first. So the actual value of the investment is significantly reduced. So
maybe it's only 75 because the husband is healthy or whatever and
the wife had a very large dowry so there's all these other
liabilities, so maybe the כתובה ketubah itself is not actually worth as
much. That is, the כתובה ketubah is not the value of the
כתובה, ketubah, the כתובה ketubah value is how much would this debt
be sold for because again, in מסכת כתובות Masechet Ketubot we also
see many examples, the wife sells her כתובה ketubah for some quick
cash now to sell off this as an investment.
האשה ha'ishah or באשה be'ishah that אשה ishah meaning maybe she'll sell
it off...
maybe she could sell it off early. I think maybe that's what
באשה be'ishah means.
Why don't we just say they use all of that? Why would
you say בעל ba'al versus אשה? ishah?
Well that's basically what רב פפא Rav Papa says. רב פפא Rav
Papa says באשה ובכתובתה be'ishah uveketubatah says take a very expansive... I
think it's... each one is moving outwards. בעל Ba'al is just is
the husband going to die sooner, not is he going to divorce
her sooner, not. באשה b'isha says we also take the woman's estate
and her liabilities and dowry etc. into the calculation. And then רב
פפא Rav Papa says ובכתובתה u'v'ktubata as well, that is her ability
to sell the כתובה Ketubah and things like that, other ways. So
you could see the גמרא's Gemara not so interested in this משנה,
mishna at least here. Obviously these questions come up in other מסכתות
Masechtot and things like that.
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot are very interested, yes.
It's not for now.
We're running late already, yeah.
Oh,
there's another issue that the משנה mishna, ignores, potentially avoiding, which is
if the court ruled based on an עדים זוממים that woman is
divorced...
No, no, no, the point is everybody, we have the witnesses on
the גט get already anyway. The point is now the case of
the גט get has come to the בית דין beit din and
they're saying okay now pay the כתובה. Ketubah. They're only we're only
concerned about the כתובה. Ketubah.
This is רש"י's Rashi thing, that the whole question is contested because
how does the... he never divorced her. Doesn't רש"י Rashi say?
Well, the husband's best claim would be to say I already paid,
presumably. Or I never divorced her
because if he says I never divorced her but then they'll say
yeah but we have the גט. get. I... so anyway don't want
to get so into it now because there's a lot to do
on עמוד ב'. amud bet. Okay. מעידים אנו באיש פלוני שהוא חייב
לחברו אלף זוז. Me'idim anu b'ish ploni shehu chayav l'chavero elef zuz.
We testify about this person that he owes his friend a thousand
זוז, zuz, על מנת ליתן לו מכאן ועד שלושים יום, al m'nat
litein lo mikan v'ad shloshim yom, that the loan was to be
paid back after thirty days. Okay. והוא אומר מכאן ועד עשר שנים.
v'hu omer mikan v'ad eser shanim. And he says yeah I do
owe him a thousand dollars but I owe it to him ten
years from now. Okay, not thirty days from now. That's a big
difference in terms of how soon the loan will be paid off
but he agrees to the debt. That's the same thing as the
husband agreeing, I did divorce her, I am going to have to
pay her the כתובה Ketubah but the question is under which... so
this is the same kind of point.
אומדים כמה אדם רוצה ליתן ויהיו בידו אלף זוז בין נותנם מכאן
ועד שלושים יום ובין נותנם מכאן ועד עשר שנים. omdim kama adam
rotze litein v'yihyu b'yado elef zuz bein notnam mikan v'ad shloshim yom
u'vein notnam mikan v'ad eser shanim. So we say how much would
someone else pay in the difference in value of having received a
loan for a month and for ten years? So you think about
it the whole idea of taking out a loan is you think
that someone else is investing in you because they know they're going
to get the money back and you now have liquid cash that
you can use to spend on all of your different enterprises. You
can go buy things, you can go build up your business and
then blah blah blah and you make back the money. So that's
the idea of taking out a loan. So there's a value in
having the loan for a longer period of time. So there's actually
is a way to assess and evaluate how much value it's worth
to have a loan for 120 times as long. It's probably somewhere
around 120 times as valuable, maybe more because ten years is a
very extended period of time to be able to put that money
into your business and grow and...
You've got a ריבית ribbit issue there.
Well not only a ריבית ribbit issue, we have a שמיטה shmita
issue. The... it's ten years. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל המלווה את חברו לעשר שנים, amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel hamalveh et chavero l'eser shanim, if you lend money to your
friend for ten years, שביעית משמטתו. shvi'it mshamtato.
The שמיטה shmita year will come in between and you'll have שמיטת
כספים. shmitat kesafim. The debt will be cancelled. So how can you
ever have this... why does the משנה mishna mention this case? It
must be that our משנה, mishna which knows about the existence of
שמיטת כספים, shmitat kesafim, must be teaching us some הלכה halacha. about
שמיטה shmita tangentially. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says אף על גב
דהשתא לא קרינן ביה לא יגוש. af al gav d'hashta lo karinan
beih lo yigosh. Even though now, that is at the time of
שמיטה, shmita, it's not called לא יגוש lo yigosh to that you
violate the prohibition of exerting pressure on the borrower to pay back,
סוף אתי לידי לא יגוש. sof ati lidei lo yigosh.
That is at the end of the loan once the loan is
collectable three years after שמיטה shmita let's say or four years after
the שמיטה shmita year whatever it is, then nonetheless at that point
once the lender comes to the borrower and says give me back
the money that's לא יגוש lo yigosh even though it doesn't take
place during the שמיטה shmita year. So that's already an interesting point.
That is we might have thought that you only violate שמיטת כספים
shmitat kesafim if actually during the שמיטה shmita year you try to
claim the... claim payment back on the loan. But if the loan
would overlap the שמיטה, shmita, it was made before שמיטה, shmita, it's
being collected after שמיטה, shmita, שמיטה shmita has nothing to do with
it perhaps. So the answer is no.
אותיב רב כהנא. otiv Rav Kahana. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana says
אומדים כמה אדם רוצה ליתן ויהיו אלף זוז בידו בין ליתן מכאן
ועד שלושים יום ובין ליתן מכאן ועד עשר שנים. omdim kama adam
rotze litein v'yihyu elef zuz b'yado bein litein mikan v'ad shloshim yom
u'vein litein mikan v'ad eser shanim. So the משנה mishna says we
have to assess in this way the difference in value between one
month and ten years. ואי אמרת שביעית משמטתו כולהו נמי לאו ליתן
רמו. v'i amart shvi'it mshamtato kulhu nami lav litein ramu. So and
if you'll tell me that שמיטה shmita cancels out this loan, then
I would have ended up concluding that actually
there's no... it would be totally valueless loan. A ten-year loan is
worth nothing, says the loan or it's worth a lot to the
borrower. It's worth nothing to the lender because the loan will be
cancelled. Okay.
ואי אמרת שביעית משמטתו כולהו נמי לאו ליתן רמו. v'i amart shvi'it
mshamtato kulhu nami lav litein ramu. So אמר רבא. amar Rava. רבא
Rava says הכא במאי עסקינן. hacha b'mai askinan. This is what we're
talking about. Cases that would not be cancelled by שמיטת כספים, shmitat
kesafim, that is במלווה b'malveh המלווה על המשכון, hamalveh al hamashkon, you
lend using collateral, which this is the last פרק perek of מסכת
שביעית Maseches Shevi'is is about שמיטת כספים. shmittas kesafim. So either if
you lend with collateral or המוסר שטרותיו לבית דין hamoser shtarosav lebeis
din or in a case where you hand over your your deed
of of the loan to the בית דין beis din for collection,
which perhaps is the same thing as פרוזבול pruzbul and perhaps is
something different than פרוזבול. pruzbul. There's a whole
מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes Rishonim about that. Okay. דתנן, Detnan, based on the
משנה mishna in מסכת שביעית, Maseches Shevi'is, המלווה על המשכון, hamalveh al
hamashkon, if you lend with a collateral, והמוסר שטרותיו לבית דין, vehamoser
shtarosav lebeis din, and you hand over your שטרות shtaros to בית
דין, beis din, אין משמיטין, ein mashmitin, those loans will not be
cancelled by שמיטה. shmittah. איכא דאמרי, Ika de'amri, אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. So there's an
alternative version of the סוגיא. sugya. So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, Rav Yehuda quotes from Shmuel, המלווה את
חברו לעשר שנים, hamalveh es chaveiro le'eser shanim, someone who lends to
his friend for ten years, אין שביעית משמטתו. ein shevi'is mshamtaso. It
actually should not be cancelled by שמיטה. shmittah. That is, this is
the inverted version of the סוגיא. sugya. We're saying oh, it's obvious
from our משנה mishna that if you lend for ten years then
שמיטה shmittah doesn't cancel it. ואף על גב דאתי לידי לא יגוש,
Ve'af al gav de'asi lidei lo yigosh, even though in the end
it will result in לא יגוש, lo yigosh, that is when you
go to collect the loan you'll be pressuring the person to pay
you, השתא מיהא לא קרינא ביה לא יגוש. hashta miha lo karina
bei lo yigosh. At the time of שמיטה, shmittah, because not collectible
yet because it's before the end of the period of the loan,
actually it's not לא יגוש lo yigosh yet. So that's actually very
interesting. We have the opposite assumption. We're assuming that there is no
violation of לא יגוש lo yigosh unless the שמיטה shmittah year, the
loan would be collectible on שמיטה. shmittah. So אמר רב כהנא, Amar
Rav Kahana, Rav Kahana says, אף אנן נמי תנינא, Af anan nami
sanina, and our משנה mishna actually proves this, עומדין כמה אדם רוצה
ליתן ביהו אלף זוז בידו בין ליתן מכאן ועד שלשים יום ובין
ליתן מכאן ועד עשר שנים. omdin kama adam rotzeh liten beihu elef
zuz beyado bein liten mikan ve'ad shloshim yom uvein liten mikan ve'ad
eser shanim. And our משנה shows proof that actually there is a
an assessable difference in value between one month and ten years collection
on the loan and therefore that ten year collection on the loan
would would work. דאי אמרת שביעית משמטתו, De'i amart shevi'is mshamtaso, so
if you would say the שמיטה shmittah year cancels it, כולהו נמי
בעי לשלומי ליה, kulhu nami ba'ei lishlumei lei, you would say that
he would have to pay back that he would have to pay
the entire value of the loan is how much it would be
worth because the loan would be cancelled. Yeah, for sure.
This sure sounds like ריבית.
ribbis. How does it sound like ריבית? ribbis?
So you're basically discounting the value of the loan.
We're not discounting. Why?
Because
because you're calculating how much how much you're willing to pay to
have the loan be able to be paid ten years in ten
years or however long's left. That is interest.
No, but again remember we're talking about different parties. We're saying if
the lender were to sell this debt to someone else, how much
would someone be willing to pay for that? This is all hypothetical
thing to assess how much Well there's two.
One is you can't exactly sell a debt. You can sell the
right to collect. Right.
But when you sell it you're
let's say I own a loan for a thousand dollars and I
sell it to I own a note for a thousand dollars. I
sell it to you for seven hundred because you aren't we aren't
sure whether it's going to get collected or not, but you're going
to eventually be able to collect a thousand dollars.
That's ריבית. ribbis.
Why is that ריבית? ribbis?
Because you bought a note for seven hundred dollars and you collect
a thousand dollars. That's three hundred dollars in interest
or why would that be? Okay
well that's another thing.
I'm talking about lending to this
person whose life is at stake there's
just different kinds
Yeah
technically you can't you can't technically I might have to look this
up but you can't technically sell a loan in הלכה.
You can sell the שטר, shtar, whatever, all different kinds of things.
Anyway, okay. So we're in the middle of this question. So אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, so Rava now responds to Rav Kahana, הכא במאי
עסקינן במלווה על המשכון ובמוסר שטרותיו לבית דין. hacha bemai askinan bemalveh
al hamashkon uvemoser shtarosav lebeis din. So we must be talking about
a case of these cases which would not be cancelled by שביעית
shevi'is and that's why our משנה mentioned it like that because those
are cases where שמיטה shmittah wouldn't cancel it. אין משמיטין. Ein mashmitin.
ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל האומר לחברו על מנת שלא תשמטני שביעית.
Ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel ha'omer lachaveiro al mnas shelo tishmteini shevi'is.
What about someone who says I make this loan to you on
the condition that the שמיטה shmittah year not cancel out the loan?
שביעית משמטתו. Shevi'is mshamtaso.
So שמיטה shmittah nonetheless will cancel out that loan. You don't have
the ability to prevent the power of the שמיטה shmittah year, though
there is a very interesting position quoted in the מרדכי, Mordechai, I
forget where, about
about how active and how passive is the lender's role in actually
having to say משמט אני mshamet ani or not. Like do you
have to give up actively or is it totally passive? So לימא
קסבר שמואל מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה תנאו בטל. Leima kasvar Shmuel
masneh al mah shekasuv batorah tena'o vatel. So because maybe Shmuel is
saying that it's making a condition about a מצוה mitzvah that's already
included in the תורה. Torah. וכל המתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה תנאו
בטל. Vechol hamasneh al mah shekasuv batorah tena'o vatel. If you make
a condition that that tries to... work around the laws of the
Torah, then that תנאי *tnai* will be totally cancelled. איתמר *Ha'itmar*, and
isn't this what this statement is saying from שמואל *Shmuel*? האומר לחבירו
על מנת שאין לך עלי אונאה *Ha'omer lechavero al menat she-ein lecha
alai ona'ah*. What if someone says I make this, I'm giving you
this money or I'm making this sale to you on the condition
that there's no אונאה *ona'ah*, there's no overcharging, that the laws of
overcharging don't apply. Now of course if someone says that to you
you say well, hmm, probably they're overcharging me, right? But anyway the
point is whether this works or not. So רבא אמר יש לו
עליו אונאה *Rava amar yesh lo alav ona'ah*, the laws of אונאה
*ona'ah* still apply. ושמואל אמר אין לו עליו אונאה *u'Shmuel amar ein
lo alav ona'ah*. So and שמואל *Shmuel* says there's no אונאה *ona'ah*,
that is, it sounds like שמואל *Shmuel* thinks you can make a
תנאי *tnai* מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה *matneh al mah she-katuv ba-Torah*.
איתמר עלה *Ha'itmar alah*, so but this was said later. אמר רב
ענן *Amar Rav Anan*, so רב ענן *Rav Anan* wants to explain
שמואל *Shmuel's* position. לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דשמואל *Lididi mifarshei li minei
de-Shmuel*, I'm going to explain שמואל *Shmuel's* position. על מנת שאין לך
עלי אונאה *Al menat she-ein lecha alai ona'ah*, I make the condition
that you have no claims of אונאה *ona'ah* against me. אין לו
עליו אונאה *Ein lo alav ona'ah*. That's when there's no אונאה *ona'ah*.
על מנת שאין בו אונאה *Al menat she-ein bo ona'ah*, if you
try to claim that the laws of אונאה *ona'ah* should not apply
to me at all, הרי יש בו אונאה *harei yesh bo ona'ah*.
So you're not allowed to make a condition that tries to undo
the law. But according to שמואל *Shmuel* you could make a תנאי
*tnai* that says I make this sale conditional on the fact that
you're not going to take me to court about it, or that
you're not going to hold me liable for this. Okay. הכא נמי
על מנת שלא תשמטני בשביעית *Hacha nami al menat she-lo tishmeteni ba-shevi'it*,
if I make a loan on the condition that you will not
nullify the loan because of שביעית *shevi'it*, אין שביעית משמטתו *ein shevi'it
mashmatato*, then the שמיטה Shmitah *shmita* year will not cancel it. על
מנת שלא תשמטני שביעית *Al menat she-lo tishmeteni shevi'it*, but on the
condition that the שמיטה Shmitah *shmita* year not cancel the loan, שביעית
משמטתו *shevi'it mashmatato*, then the שמיטה Shmitah *shmita* year will cancel it.
That is on the one you're making a תנאי *tnai* about the
person's active role in forgiving the loan or not and the second
case you're making a תנאי *tnai* about whether or not שמיטה Shmitah
*shmita* cancels loans. The first one the תנאי *tnai* will work, the
second one according to שמואל *Shmuel* the תנאי *tnai* will not work.
Okay. תניא *Tanya*. המלווה את חבירו סתם *Ha-malveh et chavero stam*. Someone
who lends money to their friend סתם *stam*, like just סתם *stam*,
whatever, that is without any specificity, אינו רשאי לתובעו פחות משלושים יום
*eino rashai letov'o pachot mishloshim yom*. If you just made a loan
you can't claim it any earlier than thirty days because the assumption
is that the normal terms of a loan barring any other specificity
would be thirty days. We saw something very similar interestingly enough by
נזיר *Nazir*. The גמרא *Gemara* goes through a whole discussion about סתם
נזירות שלושים יום *stam nezirut shloshim yom* and twenty-nine and thirty-one whatever
and the גימטריה *gematria* from the word יהיה *yihiyeh*. So it's very
interesting to consider by נזיר *Nazir* it's somehow seen as intrinsic to
the basic ritual laws of נזיר *Nazir* that the term is for
thirty days. And here in a financial context where we would think
it's totally based on the marketplace assumptions and everything else that it's
thirty days. So it's interesting that חז"ל *Chazal* are using the same
timescale. You make a סתם *stam* agreement to do something, you mean
you're going to do it within a month or you mean you'll
do it by at minimum a month and then it's interesting to
think that they use that in a ritual context where they try
to make it clear from the פסוקים *psukim* and bring all sorts
of proofs for it and here in a financial context where there's
basically no need to derive it from פסוקים *psukim* or anything like
that. Okay. And basically the answer behind that is that yeah because
thirty days is a good starting point for a basic assumption of
how much time you would want for something of this this timescale.
Okay. סבר רבה בר בר חנה קמיה דרב *Savar Rabba bar bar
Chana kamei de-Rav*. So רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba bar bar Chana*
suggests to רב *Rav*, למימר הני מילי במלווה בשטר *Lemeimar hani mili
be-milveh bi-shtar*. That's about a loan that was written out in a
שטר *shtar*, in a contract. דלא עביד איניש דטרח דכתב שטר בציר
מתלתין יומי *De-la avid inish de-tarach de-katav shtar batzir mi-tlatin yomi*. Because
nobody we can assume no one is going to go to all
of the work of hiring the סופר *sofer* and writing or printing
out the contract or writing out the contract and everything else if
the loan will be paid back less than thirty days. אבל מלווה
על פה *Aval milveh al peh*, a verbal agreement for a loan,
לא *lo*,
we can't assume that the loan is minimum thirty days. Maybe for
a verbal agreement the minimum loan is actually could be much more
minimal and maybe the claimant can come and claim the loan to
be paid back much earlier than thirty days because there's no assumption
that it would be minimum thirty days. Okay. תניא נמי הכי *Tanya
nami hachi*. We have a ברייתא *braita* that supports this. המלווה את
חבירו סתם *Ha-malveh et chavero stam*. If you lend money to your
friend without any specificity, אינו רשאי לתובעו פחות משלושים יום *eino rashai
letov'o pachot mishloshim yom*. You can't go and claim the loan for
less than thirty days. אחד המלווה בשטר ואחד המלווה על פה *Echad
ha-malveh bi-shtar ve-echad ha-malveh al peh*. Whether it's recorded in a שטר
*shtar* or whether it was a verbal agreement. אמר ליה Amar Lei
שמואל לרב מתנא *Amar lei Shmuel le-Rav Matna*, לא תיתיב אכרעך עד
דפרשת לה להא שמעתא *Lo titeiv akareicha ad de-parshaht lah l'ha shmaita*.
I'm not going to let you get up off of your sitting
down until you explain to me this teaching. this until you explain
to me this הלכה because it seems very strange. How could it
be minimum thirty days both for an oral loan and a written
loan? So מנא הני מילתא? Mena Hani Milta? So what case are
we doing? דאמרו רבנן המלוה את חברו סתם אינו רשאי לתובעו פחות
משלושים יום אחד המלוה בשטר
ואחד המלוה על פה. Deamru Rabbanan Hamalveh Et Chavero Stam Eino Rashai
Letov'o Pachot Mishloshim Yom Echad Hamalveh Bish’tar Veechad Hamalveh Al Peh. So
that's what he was asking him about. אמר ליה דכתיב, Dechtiv, it's
based on this פסוק Pasuk קרבה שנת השבע שנת השמיטה. Kar’vah Shnat
Hasheva Shnat Hashmitah. The שמיטה year is coming soon for the
seventh year, the year of releasing. So he says what? ממשמע שנאמר
קרבה שנת השבע, Mimashma Shene’emar Kar’vah Shnat Hasheva, from the fact that
it says the seventh year is soon, איני יודע שהיא שנת שמיטה?
Eini Yode’a Shehie Shnat Shmitah? Do I not know from context that
he's talking about the שמיטה year? אלא מה תלמוד לומר שנת השמיטה,
Ela Ma Talmud Lomar Shnat Hashmitah, the year of releasing the loans,
לומר לך יש שמיטה אחרת שהיא כזאת. Lomar Lecha Yesh Shmitah Acheret
Shehie Kazot. There is another שמיטה that is like this. That is
what? ואיזו זו המלוה את חברו סתם שאינו רשאי לתובעו פחות משלושים
יום. Ve’eizu Zu Hamalveh Et Chavero Stam She’eino Rashai Letov’o Pachot Mishloshim
Yom. That the minimum terms for an ambiguous loan are taken to
be minimally thirty days. That is, that's like a שמיטה in that
what? In that you're not allowed to claim back, meaning I say,
oh I only loaned it to you for two days, I want
the money now, you say no, if you wanted it within that
time you should have made it explicit at the time we made
the agreement. Okay, דאמר מר שלושים יום בשנה חשוב שנה, De’amar Mar
Shloshim Yom Beshanah Chashuv Shanah, because thirty days out of the year
for certain kinds of cases at the end of the year the
last month could be counted as a full year for certain things
and this is a whole different context sometimes we require for the
fiscal year or something like that that we would require a little
bit of the year to count, you know, how many years did
we make this agreement for? Well what's the cutoff? Is it from
day to day and we just go year to year from that
day? Or do we say the first year would be a minimal
piece of this year and then we'll start again from the new
year that'll be the second year? We see this in the beginning
of מסכת ראש השנה Masechet Rosh Hashanah the discussion of kings and
things like that, all of those questions there and
it comes up by חזקה Chazakah all in בבא בתרא Bava Batra
all the questions about in third פרק Perek and all the different
things about מצרין Metzarin and all these questions. So when you have
land deals as well, how many years are you going to be
leased out the land and things like that? So thirty days out
of the year would count towards a year for many of those
agreements. Okay. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב Ve’amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav
הפותח בית הצוואר, Hapotayach Beit Hatzavar,
so let's start there tomorrow actually because that's a whole different topic.
So wonderful, hope everyone has a great day and I'll see you
tomorrow.
Thank you.